<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine proposals of divers attorneys of the Court of Common-Pleas, for the regulating the proceedings at law, and remedying some inconveniences: whereby the clyent will be much secured, the processe shortned, the greatest part of the charge of most suits abated, many unnecessary suits in law and equity prevented, and the creditor and purchaser well provided for: and thereby lending, trade and commerce advanced: which is the end and desire of the proposers. / Presented to the honourable committee for the regulating proceedings in law Decemb. 5. 1650.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E622_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865594</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165789</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78485)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165789)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E622[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine proposals of divers attorneys of the Court of Common-Pleas, for the regulating the proceedings at law, and remedying some inconveniences: whereby the clyent will be much secured, the processe shortned, the greatest part of the charge of most suits abated, many unnecessary suits in law and equity prevented, and the creditor and purchaser well provided for: and thereby lending, trade and commerce advanced: which is the end and desire of the proposers. / Presented to the honourable committee for the regulating proceedings in law Decemb. 5. 1650.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Lee and D. Pateman, and are to be sold at their shops in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650 [i.e. 1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Common Pleas --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Complex litigation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Procedure (Law) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Costs (Law) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165789:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE PROPOSALS OF Divers ATTORNEYS of the Court of COMMON-PLEAS, For the regulating the proceedings at Law, and remedying ſome Inconveniences: Whereby the Clyent will be much ſecured, the Proceſſe ſhortned, the greateſt part of the charge of moſt Suits abated, many unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Suits in Law and Equity prevented, and the Creditor and Purchaſer well provided for: and thereby Lending, Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce advanced: <hi>Which is the end and deſire of the Propoſers.</hi> Preſented to the Honourable Committe for the regulating proceedings in Law <hi>Decem.</hi> 5. 1650.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>W. Lee</hi> and <hi>D. Pateman,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhops in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165789:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165789:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE the COMMITTEE aſsigned by Authority of Parliament for regulating the proceedings at LAW.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The humble Propoſers obſerving ſome unneceſſary charges and delay introduced by the corruption and multitude of Offices and Officers, which ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, beſides ſome inconveniences that the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time had produced, the ſame being more obvious to them then others by reaſon of their experience in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Law: for remedy thereof conſulted how to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to the Parliament, and to that purpoſe had ſeverall meetings together, wherein the Propoſals now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your view were agreed on, as things that would conduce much to the eaſe, benefit, and ſafety of the Suiter, ſecurity of Creditors and Purchaſors, make good proviſion againſt the moſt generall inconveniences, prevent many frivolous and unneceſſary ſuits, both at Law and in equity, ſhorten the proceſſe in many, and eaſe the charge in all; and (which is not the leaſt of their ambitions) take away thoſe aſperſions that ſeem to blemiſh that Law, the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:165789:3"/>which they humbly conceive to be the moſt perfect Law of any humane Law in the World; a Law that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits <hi>Nullum abſurdum,</hi> that admits nothing againſt the Laws of God or nature, againſt reaſon, or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to any other Learning, wherein all matters of fact are adjudged and tried by twelve able diſcreet and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different neighbours to the place where the matter of fact ariſes, and the matters of Law are debated, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, and determined by as many of the moſt ancient, grave, and learned Lawyers of the whole Common wealth, who for their great experience, integrity, and wiſdome, are firſt deſervedly called to the ſtate and degree of Serjeants at Law, and after to be Judges; and the proceſſe of this Law is ſo quicke, that it ſeldome happens any cauſe at Law depends above three or foure Termes; but covetouſneſſe, the root of all evill having built ſome Flood-gates upon the chanell thereof, whereby the courſe hath been obſtructed, ſtopt, or diverted out of its due courſe, and thereby more care taken to catch the Fiſh for the benefit of the Officers, then for the diſpatch or advance of the Clients buſineſſe, and the Propoſers being unwilling to treſpaſſe upon the Freehold of others by pulling down the Wares themſelves, have by the drawing the chanell a neerer way in ſome Caſes, and in other upon a lower flat, have nevertheleſſe ſo orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the buſineſſe, as they humbly conceive that most of the Griſt will be ground without paying Toll at thoſe unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Milnes. And becauſe Reformation wreſtles with many difficulties, it being hard to finde an <hi>Epheſus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome <hi>Demetrius,</hi> or ſome Criticke that will conclude the Shrubs ſeeke the fall of the Cedars, hoping thereby to advance their own tops: the Propoſers have been very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not to propoſe any thing that may in the leaſt degree ſeem to advance their own Intereſts, but many things that
<pb facs="tcp:165789:3"/>will turn to their particular loſſe, they alwaies preferring the publique good before their own particular intereſts. Neither have they raſhly herein proceeded, having at leaſt ſpent ten moneths in the conception, digeſting, conſidering on, and compoſing of what they now preſent to your more grave conſiderations; and as they are not the iſſues of raſh braines, ſo they have not paſſed without peruſall and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many others of good judgement and experience, and are now to live and die under your Honourable cenſures: whereby if you ſhall receive any light to the furthering the good work in hand, or the Republique any benefit the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers have their wiſhed ends, and humbly therein ſubmit themſelves and theſe their poore labours to your better judgements, by the hands of the moſt humbleſt of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servants, S. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165789:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165789:4"/>
            <head>The humble Propoſals of divers of the Attorneyes of the Court of <hi>Common-pleas,</hi> as the ſame were agreed on at their laſt generall meeting held at <hi>Staple-Inne</hi> upon Friday the <hi>24</hi> day of <hi>May,</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1650.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Theſe Fines are the 200th part of the thing deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, be it land, debt, or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and muſt be paid at the Plaintiffes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into his ſuite, though he never reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any thing.</note> They humbly propoſe and conceive that Fines upon Originall Writs are againſt the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall reaſon of the Common Lawes of this Realm, which never impoſeth Fines upon any but offenders: But theſe <hi>Addere afflictionem afflictis,</hi> are exacted of the party injured, who comes to ſue for Juſtice, when the party delinquent too oft eſcapes the puniſhment. And therefore they humbly propoſe that the ſame may be taken away, and no more payd or demanded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They humbly conceive that the meane Proces in ſuing to the Utlary are unneceſſary,
<note place="margin">This is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to prevent the chatge and delay which the Clyent is now at, who muſt be two Termes in ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, and is beſides the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay put to the charge of three <hi>Capias,</hi> which are commonly ſued forth altogether, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned altogether in the Sheriffs name, but by the Attorney, but by this courſe of ſuing to the Utlary the proces will be a Terme ſhorter, and 5 s. 10 d. leſſe charge, beſides the Fine, if fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and the proceedings by way of Summons will caſe us of common Bailyes, and make ſure that ſuits will come to iſſue in two Terms.</note> and doe tend onely to charge and delay: And therefore they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſe that upon two ſummons being made in Writing to the Defendant perſonally, or left with ſome diſcreet perſon (<hi>viz.</hi> ſome perſon of <hi>Sanae memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> and above the age of fixteen yeeres) of his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the Sheriffe or his known Officer, and returned ſerved by him upon Record, the party Plaintiffe may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165789:5"/>proceed to judgement in all perſonall actions in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following, without appearance of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. (That is to ſay) the firſt Summons to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by ſeven daies before the day of appearance in form aforeſaid, the party Plaintiff may enter his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration in Court; and in caſe no apparance be made thereunto within eight daies, that then a new Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the nature of a <hi>Scire facias</hi> briefly containing the matter of the Declaration to be awarded upon the Imparlance Roll to ſummon the Defendant to appeare at a certaine day to come againſt him, at which day if the party doe not appeare within eight daies after and plead, and the Sheriffe returne him ſummoned by ſeven daies, in forme aforeſaid, that then Rules having been duely given in Court to that purpoſe, judgement ſhall be given againſt ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant by his default: and that in all perſonall actions iſſues may be returned upon the <hi>Venire facias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to triall upon the <hi>Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re facias</hi> wil bring many cauſes to triall a Terme ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and wil eaſe the charge about 4 s. 11 d. in a Cauſe.</note> &amp; Writs of <hi>niſi prius</hi> awarded, and trials had, <hi>&amp; tales de circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantibus</hi> granted thereupon as formerly upon the <hi>habeas corpora &amp; diſtring as jurat,</hi> provided the Jury be returned ten daies at leaſt before the trial of the cauſe, and that no Eſſoyne ſhall or may be allowed upon the returne of any of the ſaid Writs of ſummons or <hi>venire facias;</hi> and in all other proces the ancient courſe to be obſerved which is onely propoſed by way of ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">It is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that the Writ of <hi>Capias</hi> ſhall be taken away firſt, becauſe many perſons have no certain places of abode. Secondly the way of ſummons being a new manner of proceeding, the propoſers doubt the ſucceſſe may not anſwer their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and expectations. Thirdly, becauſe in ſome caſes the party plaintiffe may have juſt cauſe to require ſpeciall baile, of which if deprived, he would be in danger to loſe the benefit of his ſuit, and therefore the propoſers humbly conceive it better by finding out neerer and cheaper waies to bring the old road to be neglected, then to deprive the ſuiter of the old before he hath experience of the new.</note> and not to take away the ancient courſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding by way of <hi>Capias</hi> and <hi>Exigent,</hi> if the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it. But if ſo, then the <hi>Exigent</hi> to be awarded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165789:5"/>the returne of the firſt <hi>Capias,</hi> as formerly upon the <hi>plur. Capias,</hi> and as it is now uſed after judgement. And for encouragement of the Shieriffs in the due execution of the ſaid proceſſe, They humbly propoſe that the like Fees may be paid upon the <hi>Venire facias</hi> for ſummoning the Jury, as formerly upon the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringas jur. &amp; habeas corpora,</hi> and that two ſhillings foure pence may be paid for every Summons to be made, the Shieriffe undertaking to doe the ſame in due time, <hi>viz.</hi> foure pence for a Warrant, twelve pence to the Baily that makes the Summons, and twelve pence for the Shieriffs regard; And that he ſhal receive likewiſe twelve pence for the returne of every Summons duely made; and that the Plantiffe may lay his Action in the proper County where the cauſe of Action ſhall ariſe, notwithſtanding the Summons goe out into a forraigne County, where the parties dwel, and that without the delay of <hi>teſtatums,</hi> and that ſo all ſucceeding proceſſe may iſſue into any County with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>teſtatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They humbly conceive the recovery of Rents,
<note place="margin">The Proceſſe In <hi>Replevin</hi> at this day is ſo delatory, that if the Plaintiffe will (who upon the matter is defendant) he may delay the Avowant two or three yeers, for after long delay in the County Court, he may make a long and delatory defence after removall, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to iſſue and triall, and then become Nonſuit, whereupon the avowant ſhal have a <hi>Returna bahend.</hi> the Proceſſe whereupon wil ſpend wel nigh a yeere, and then the Plaintiffe may ſue a ſecond deliverance which ſupercedes the avowants Proceſſe and puts him to a new proceeding to triall, which wil ſpend a great part of another yeere; but by the courſe propoſed, three Terms wil diſpatch the buſineſſe, as in other caſes.</note> Services, damages for Treſpaſſes, and other duties by way of diſtreſſe, is both a ready and ancient courſe, and prevents many unneceſſary ſuits, but by the intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and prolix proceſſe thereof, the ſame is very much abuſed, and from thence neglected. They therefore humbly propoſe, that a nonſuit in a <hi>Replevin</hi> may be perem ptory againſt the Plaintiffe; and that if the ſame ſhall happen upon triall, the Jury ſworne for triall of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165789:6"/>the iſſue may inquire of the Avowants damage. But if otherwiſe then a Writ to enquire of damage to iſſue, and finall judgement to be thereupon given in both caſes, and that againſt the Defendant like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe may iſſue by way of Summons, and judgement had as aforeſaid, without the unneceſſary proceedings in the County Court.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They humbly conceive that the long delay, that reall Actions admits is the occaſion,
<note place="margin">One halſe of all trials on Ejectments fall off upon ſome defect or other in theſe points which reach not at all to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the cauſe.</note> that all titles, where the entry is not taken away, have of late beene tryed in Ejectments, which for that purpoſe are very uſefull; but there being ſo many circumſtances in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Leaſe, entry and ouſter neceſſary to be proved upon tryall, that many tryals have, and continually doe miſcarry thereby to the great delay and dammage of the Clyent; they therefore humbly propoſe that all Ejectments ſhall be brought againſt the preſent Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and occupiers of the Lands in queſtion, againſt whom ſuch proceſſe by way of Summons ſhall iſſne, as aforeſaid: And that upon triall of the iſſue the Leaſe, entry and ouſter ſhall be admitted, and the title onely inſiſted upon, and that for the better ſetling Poſſeſſions according to right; and by the Common Law it may be provided, that if any perſon or perſons after any poſſeſſion ſhall be delivered by Writ of <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<note place="margin">This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſettle the poſſeſſion by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, for at this day after the Clyent hath ſetled the title at Law, which often proves tedious enough, he cannot ſettle the poſſeſſion without a Decree in Chancery, and here is no proviſion made for thoſe that enter to make Leaſes for triall of titles, becauſe they may proceed by Summons againſt the Tenant of the Land if they wil, according to the ſecond Propoſall.</note> facias poſſeſſionem,</hi> or other legall proceſſe ſhall again ouſt the party, or voluntarily diſtribute the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions ſo delivered without legall proceſſe warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame, that then a Writ in the nature of a Writ <hi>Redeſeiſme</hi> may iſſue to the Sheriffe to re-eſtabliſh the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165789:6"/>poſſeſſion in the Plantiffe, and to give dammage, &amp;c. as in caſe of <hi>Redeſeiſme</hi> hath been uſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They humbly conceive that the Common Barre and new aſſignment in actions of treſpaſſe,
<note place="margin">The Common barre and new Aſſignment puts the Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in every Action of treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe <hi>quare clauſum fregit,</hi> that comes to triall to at leaſt twelve ſhillings charge and may be ſupplied by three or foure words in the Declaration, and put the Clyent to no charge at all, and the recitall of the Writ in many Actions almoſt doubles the charge to the Clyent, and is uſeleſſe.</note> 
               <hi>quare clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum fregit,</hi> and the recitall of the Originall Writ in actions of treſpaſſe, and upon the Caſe, and ſeverall other actions are ſuperfluous things, and infinitely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the charge of the Clyent: They therefore humbly propoſe, that in all Actions of Treſpaſſe, <hi>quare cauſum fregit,</hi> the place may be aſſigned in the Count, And that for the future there may be no more reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of the Originall Writ, other then in the forme en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, (that is to ſay) <hi>A. B. attach. fuit ad reſpondend. C. D. de placito tr.</hi> or <hi>de placito tr. ſuper caſum,</hi> or the like, as is obſerved in the Upper Bench; and the Originals in all perſonal actions to be made according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without repetition of the ſpeciall matter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They humbly conceive,
<note place="margin">Many Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverſed for want of Originals, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happens becauſe the Attorney ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then he wil pay a <hi>poſt Terminum</hi> or more, which is twenty pence a Terme, he wil hazzard his Clyents cauſe, which Fee was ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally intended as a puniſhment upon the Attorney for his neglect; but it turnes too oft to the deſtruction of the Clyent: and therefore the Propoſers have propoſed the puniſhment to returne to the Clyents reliefe and not deſtruction. Other times this miſchiefe happens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an Attorney pethaps may forget in due time to ſue out the Originall, and after when he ſees the default, he would amend it, but the Creditors holding a courſe for their own benefit that no Originall Writ can be ſued forth returnable of a former Terme, but within the firſt weeke of the enſuing Terme, the Attorney is therefore reſtrained to doe his duty to his Clyent.</note> that by reaſon Originall Writs are not duely ſued forth and filed, many judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are daily reverſed, and in the time to come are ſubject to the like inconvenience by the careleſneſſe neglect or forgetfulneſſe of the Attorney or Clark, or to ſave <hi>poſt Terminunis</hi> which turnes much to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Clyent: And therefore they humbly propoſe that from henceforth there may be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165789:7"/>but that the Plaintiffe may at any time before the want thereof aſſigned for Error, ſue forth and fyle any Originall Writ, or other Writ to make good or warrant any judgement. And that for the fyling of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Writs no <hi>poſt Terminum</hi> be demanded or payd; and that then, if any Judgement happen to be reverſed for default of Original Writ, the Clark or Attorney in whoſe default the ſame ſhall be, ſhall and may be fined in ſuch ſumme to be payd to the party grieved, as the Court ſhall (having reſpect to the quality of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) think meet and impoſe.</p>
            <p>They hvmbly conceive alſo that the not due fyling of Warrants of Attorney,
<note place="margin">The Warrant of Attorney originally ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of good uſe, but now it. is onely fyled by the Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and is of no uſe at all, but puts the Clyent to ſome charges and much hazzard, for that the want thereof is ſufficient cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe a Judgement, and the fyling now of no uſe.</note> which through forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or careleſneſſe is often neglected, is very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the Clyent, and yet of no benefit or uſe at all, and therefore they humbly ſubmit it to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Parliament whether the ſame be not fit to be diſcontinued, and the penall Statutes for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning thereof repealed.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <note place="margin">This is the moſt unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable charge upon the Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that can be invented, which is the tenth part of what dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſoever the Plaintiffe recovers: as if the Defendant upon a bargaine promiſe to give the Plaintiffe a 1000 <hi>li.</hi> which he recovers in dammage, the Prothonotary ſhall have 100 <hi>li.</hi> and doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it, nor can juſtifie the giving of any coſts for it was originally, as is conceived exacted by the Clergy as a perſonall Tythe, the Clergymen being the Clerkes that Writ to all or the moſt of the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
               </note> They humbly conceive, that <hi>Dammage Cleare</hi> is both a great and unreaſonable burden to the Clyent, who after a long and tedious ſuit, muſt have his Debt or other duty Tythed; a duty anciently belonging to the Clergy, but is now converted to an improper uſe (as they humbly conceive) And therefore they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſe, that the ſame may be taken away, and no more payd or demanded.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165789:7"/>
            <p n="9">9. They humbly conceive,
<note place="margin">The ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry charge of a Fine comes to about three pound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the fine and poſt ſine, which is the fourth part of the yearly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary charges of a recovery, comes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4 l. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the fiue, which comes to a tenth part of the yearely value, but if done by attor ney, and not in perſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to much more, and theſe ſo dangerous too that the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſeneſſe or knavery of an Attorney, or Officer may leave them at faſt and looſe, and the ſatisfaction a purchaſor can receive by them is nothing at all, for that no man, but the parties privy can tel of what Lands they be ſued forth off, when as a deed inrolled may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled in both offices, for a ten or twenty ſhillings charge that ſhal containe all certainties, and ſubject to no error: and though Statutes by reaſon of the general Office may be found, yet purchaſors ſhal never be ſecured againſt judgements and recognizances without ſuch courſe; perhaps it may be objected, that many that owe moneys, and make morgages, would be loath that their conditions ſhould be known; and that it would be a hinderance to commerce and trade; to which it is anſwered, that it is better that ſuch commerce ſhould be loſt, whereby much honeſt trade wil be advanced, for that men wil freely and frankly trade, lend, buy, &amp;c. when they know they cannot be cozened in their aſſurances, but here as in all other caſes, the propoſers leave fines, and recoveries, being very ancient and authentick conveyance to the Clyent to uſe, or not to uſe.</note> that Fines and Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for cutting off Intailes are both a great charge to the Clyent, and very dangerous in point of Error, and the ſame containe not any ſuch certainty of the lands, as were neceſſary to ſatisfie and ſecure Purchaſors and Creditors, and that alſo Intailes are very dangerous to them, and were firſt obtained, and ſince continued to avoid forfeitures, which they humbly conceive, is not proper to a well governed Common-wealth; and therefore they humbly propoſe, that Tennant in tayle may be impowred to alien, as if he had the abſolute Feeſimple; and that as well the Lands of the Tenant in tayle; as alſo the Copyhold Eſtate of Copyholders may be ſubject to their debts in whoſe hands ſoever they come, as other Freehold Lands in Fee ſimple are, and that ſuch Alienation by Tennant in tayle, and all other Eſtates made of any Lands, Tenements, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hereditaments, or of any rent, or other profit iſſuing out of the ſame, ſhall not be valued as againſt a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny creditor or purchaſor for valuable conſideration, before the ſame be inrolled in ſome inrollment Office to be eſtabliſhed in the proper County, and tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and alſo inrolled in ſome generall Office of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollments in or about <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165789:8"/>of effect as againſt ſuch purchaſors and creditors one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the time of the inrollment thereof, and that Offices be erected as well for the doing thereof, as alſo for the briefe entring, inrollment, and recording of all Judgements, Statutes, and recognizances, to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution whereof any Lands, Tenements, or other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments is or ſhall be ſubject or lyable; and they likewiſe to be of force as againſt ſuch Purchaſors, and Creditors from the time of the inrollment onely, and that reaſonable Fees may be ſetled by the ſheet containing certaine numbers of words for the doing of the ſame. And they humbly propoſe, that ſuch deeds inrolled ſhall be of the ſame effect as Fines are, and were either at common Law, or by any Statute, Feme coverts being duly examined by the Recorders or Regiſters (who they deſire may be men of great integrity, judgement, and worth;) and one Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace, as formerly upon the taking the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of fines hath beene obſerved.
<note place="margin">If the Clyent becauſe he can get no Proces ſerved upon the Defendant be forced to utlaw him, and then be forced to ſeiz his Land to force him in, the profit goes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> and the Clyent loſeth all, or elſe ſhal be put to the charge of a Leaſe which wil lye him in above 20. Markes, and 4 l. or thereabouts yearely to continue it, and then if the party plead ſome feigned Title, or reverſe the Utlawry, all is loſt, and it is deſired, that if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conceive it fit, that this Propoſal be reduced to a Law, that care may be taken in the penning it, that the <hi>Exchequer</hi> Clerks may not evade it, for that lowable Lawes wil not hold them.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. And whereas the Clyent is often inforced to utlaw the Defendant by reaſon he abſents himſelfe; and after a long chargeable, and tedious ſuit, is put alſo to ſeize the Defendants Eſtate, and expects thereby to receive the benefit of his ſuit, when contrary to the poor ſuiters expectation, the whole benefit is ſwept into the Exchequer. They therefore for remedy thereof humbly propoſe, that the Plaintiffe in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may have the benefit of all ſeizures upon Utlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165789:8"/>till his debt, or other dammages with reaſonable coſts be ſatisfied and paid; and that to that end Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe may iſſue out of the Exchequer, by which the Sherriffe may be authorized, and commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver all ſuch Goods, and Chattels, and ſatisfie and pay all ſuch moneys by him to be levyed to the Plaintiffe, until he be ſatisfied of his debt or dammages, with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable coſts to be aſſeſſed by the ſaid Court; and that afterwards the Sheriffe be accomptable in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, for the profits,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment having already obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of Writs of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt the miſchiefes of them, but the propoſers having contrived this propoſal before that was publiſhed, and finding (as they conceive) that the new Act will not produce that good effect that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, they have preſumed to proceed upon their former grounds, and humbly preſent theſe Caſes which they conceive are not provided for by the ſaid Act.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The new Act onely remedies after Verdict, and they humbly conceive other Caſes are within the ſame miſchiefe, and deſerve as much favour, for that thoſe that come to tryal are moſt commonly frivilous wrangling Actions, when the other are for ſecuring debts upon bond, and often of great value.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is that no Writ of Error ſhould be a <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> &amp;c. And they conceive that it onely takes away the <hi>Superſedeas</hi> by the Writ of Error, but not that which is curſitorily made upon the Wit of Error.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Admitting it doth take away all <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> which they humbly conceive was intended yet becauſe the Act doth not appoint what Court ſhal make the execution, they humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Act availes little, ſince the Common Pleas, or inferiour Court, after the Record removed cannot make out execution, nor the upper Bench till it is affirmed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The New Act gives double coſts but becauſe it doth not give execution for them, it is humbly conceived the party is put to his action of debt for them wherein he ſhal have no coſts</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It provides that nothing ſhal be moved in arreſt or ſtay of Judgement but matter of ſubſtance appearing in the Declaration and proceeding after, ſo that they conceive all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>deborſt le Record</hi> is excluded, wherein though the intention of the Parliament was good, yet it is conceived that if the party be ſurpriſed for want of notice, or that a Jury miſcarry themſelves in giving their Verdict, and many other accidents of like nature, within the ſtrict letter cannot be allowed in arreſt of Judgement, which it is humbly conceived was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be reſtrained by the Parliament.</p>
               </note> as before times hath been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And alſo when as the Clyent having run over all the Proceſſe and having obtained Judgement, and expecting his execution thereupon, Writs of Errors are often brought for delay, which though we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive our former propoſals will make good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165789:9"/>proviſion againſt, yet the ſame being a <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> and admitting long Proceſſe, it is often more coſtly and dangerous to the Clyent, then all that hath proceeded; and though they humbly conceive appeales juſt and uſeful, yet to prevent the inconveniences thereof, they humbly propoſe, that no <hi>Superſedeas</hi> upon a Writ of Error be from henceforth made forth or allowed, but that the Court where the original Judgement was entred, may make forth execution, as though no ſuch Writ of Error had been brought, or record tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, unleſſe the party proſecuting the ſame depoſite in Court, the money or other duty recovered, or give ſufficient Baile, to ſatisfie the Judgement with the coſts and dammage awarded, in caſe the ſame Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be affirmed, or the Writ of Error diſcontinued or abated, or the Plaintiffe therein nonſuited; and that the death of any party to the ſaid ſuit ſhal not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſuch baile; and that from henceforth no Writ of Error ſhal be received or allowed, unleſſe the ſame by returnable within eight dayes, if there ſhal be ſo many in Terme; and if there ſhal not happen to be eight dayes in Terme, then at the firſt returne of the next enſuing Terme; and that the Plaintiffe in ſuch Writ of Error ſhal without any <hi>ſcire facias,</hi> aſſigne his Errors within foure dayes after the return of the ſaid Writ, whereunto the Defendant in the ſaid Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror may if he will appear <hi>gratis,</hi> and be at liberty to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge dimunution, or joyne in iſſue, and proceed to the examination of the Errors; and that in caſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be affirmed, and it appear any ſuch Writ of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror ſhal be brought meerely for delay, or that the matter aſſigned ſhal not be difficult, or abide argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then the party Plaintiffe in the ſaid Writ of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165789:9"/>to pay to the Defendant for his or their delay therein treble coſts, and dammage; and in caſe of nonſuite or diſcontinuance before argument, double coſts, and in caſe of abatement, or in ſuch caſes where the matter ſhal be difficult ſingle coſts and damma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; and that the parties may have thereof like exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution as for the principal debt, or dammages.</p>
            <p n="12">12. They humbly conceive it fit,
<note place="margin">There is (by reaſon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law hath no compulſary Proceſſe) no remedy, but in <hi>Chancery</hi> for Legacies, where if the Legacy be ſmal, it is quickly ſpent with a great overplus.</note> that ſome legal courſe were provided for the recovery of Legacies, and that the Clyent ſhould not be forced to an equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſe in <hi>Chancery</hi> for every petit Legacy, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy whereby often proves worſe then the diſeaſe. They therefore humbly propoſe, that an Action of debt, Trover, detinue, or other action, as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires may lye at common Law for the ſame, and that therein the thing demanded upon due proof made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tryal may be recovered with coſts and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and like defence, and proceſſe may be had therein, as in ſuch other Actions are, or ſhal be uſed at Common Law.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <note place="margin">As the Law now ſtands, the heire may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat all credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, for if he fear the debts of the Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, he may alien the ſame day his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor dies, and leave the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor no <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> to bring his action, and though it is true that fraud may be averred, yet few frauds are hard to be proved.</note> They humbly conceive it very hard to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor, that the bare alienation of an heir ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat him of a juſt debt, the ſame being often done meerely in fraud, when perhaps the creditors money purchaſed the Land diſcending; and therefore they humbly propoſe, that an Action of debt may lye againſt the heire in all caſes, as wel after as before alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and that his Perſon, Goods, and Land, may be ſubject to the execution for the debt of his Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters upon ſpecialty, to the value of the Land diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Fee ſimple, or Fee tayle; and that ſuch action, and this propoſall, may (if the Parliament ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165789:10"/>meet) be extended to the heires of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, as wel as Freeholders.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <note place="margin">Many perſons run into debt to buy Land, gaine liberty in priſon, and there live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other mens Eſtates, and laugh them to ſcorne, which this it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt.</note> They humbly propoſe, that in caſe any debtor ſhal continue in priſon upon any execution or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Law for due debt, above a year, or continue outlawed after judgement above a year after notice thereof, that then at the prayer of the Plaintiffe, a Writ in the nature of a <hi>fierifacias</hi> may iſſue out of the Court, from whence the Proceſſe iſſued, whereupon he continued ſo in priſon, directed to the Sheriffe, whereby the ſaid Sheriffe ſhal be impowred to levy the ſaid debt and coſts by the ſale of the Lands, Goods, Tenements, and other eſtate, which ſuch debtor ſhal have in poſſeſſion, uſe or truſt in the hands of another, and ſatisfie the creditor therewith ſo far as the ſame wil extend, and then the priſoner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to bee diſcharged. And whereas the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor is often defrauded of his juſt debt by the frauds, and coven of Executors, and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. For remedy thereof they humbly propoſe, that in all caſes, where Executors or Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſhall ſuffer Judgement by <hi>Nihil dicit, nonſum informatus,</hi> or confeſſion, that Aſſets ſhall be preſumed, and execution iſſue immediately againſt their Perſons and eſtates, and that upon all Tryalls of <hi>plene admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtravit,</hi> the defendant ſhall exhibite a true Inventory, and the Judge before whom ſuch Tryall ſhall be had may be authorized to examine ſuch defend. or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants upon oath to the truth of the ſame, or other wiſe Aſſets to be preſumed, provided that in caſe the party defendant ſhall happen to beſick, or have neceſſary occaſion to be abſent at the time of the ſaid Tryall, that then if the defendant or defendants ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165789:10"/>fore any Judge of the ſame Court where ſuch cauſe ſhall be depending before the ſaid Tryall,
<note place="margin">At this day if an executor give Judgment by default, the plaintiffe muſt either procure the Sherriffe to returne a <hi>deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtavit</hi> which will not be had but by bribes and ſecurity, or elſe he muſt proceede by way of inquiry, which is a very queſtionable way, and as ſeemes very dangerous for defendants for if an Inqueſt of office finde aſſetts, the defendant hath legally no remedy, though in ſtrict Law he hath no way to avoyd it, having no day in Court after judgement, nor <hi>attaint</hi> againſt the Jury; and now becauſe the Civil Law hath no compulſatory proceſſe, it is hard to charge Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors or Adminiſtrators with an Inventory, and thoſe that are then delivered in are careleſly received, and the oath for the truth thereof too often not duly adminiſtred.</note> and exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite an Jnventory, and be examined to the truth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon oath, or ſhall come before any two Juſtices of the Peace of the County where ſuch cauſe ſhall be tryed, giving the plantiffe or his Attorney notice ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſhall there exhibite an Inventory, and be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined upon oath to ſuch reaſonable queſtions as the plaintiffe or his Attorney, or ſuch Juſtice on his behalf in his abſence ſhall propound concerning the truth thereof, that then ſuch Inventory ſhall be as effectuall as if the ſame had beene exhibited in forme aforeſaid upon Tryall of the ſaid cauſe, and that the Judges and Juſtices aforeſaid may be impowred to adminiſter and examine upon oath as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="15">15. They humbly propoſe,
<note place="margin">The preſent inconvenience concerning Tythes is very great, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law not having power to proceed, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law onely for predial Tythes, wherein though treble dammage be given, yet becauſe there is no coſts they are not worth ſuing for, unleſſe of ſome conſiderable value, and Juſtices of Peace, few of them being Lawyers, cannot wel judge therein.</note> that in caſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhal thinke fit to continue payment of Tythes, that then an Action of debt, detinue or treſpaſſe may lie generally at Common Law for the ſame, as wel before ſetting forth as after, wherein dammage and coſts may be recovered, as in other like Actions at Common law.</p>
            <p n="16">16. They humbly propoſe, that for the avoyding of unneceſſary and frivolous ſuits at Law, that it may be enacted, that if any Attorney or Sollicitor ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite in the defence or proſecution of his Clyents
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165789:11"/>cauſe any other or larger ſumme or ſummes then ſo much as the charge thereof ſhall ſurmount unto in <hi>Eaſter Terme, Trinity Terme</hi> and the ſhort Vacation, or in one other Terme and Vacation, that then ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney or Sollicitor ſhall be without all remedy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the ſame againſt the Clyent at Law.</p>
            <p n="17">17. And for the further avoyding of the frivolous ſuits at Law,
<note place="margin">In Replevin at Common-law tender of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends before impounding in all caſes was a good barre, and by the Statute 21. <hi>Jac.</hi> in treſpaſſe, for involuntary treſpaſſes tender of amends is made a good plea being done before Action brought; but becauſe many times impoundings and actions are made and brought perhaps before the Defendant hath any knowledge of the treſpaſſe, this propoſall is preſented: But for voluntary treſpaſſes it is conceived fit to leave them at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law to prevent greater inconveniencies.</note> they humbly propoſe, that tender of ſufficient amends with coſts for all involuntary Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes may be a good barre in all Replevins and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Treſpaſſe brought for the ſame, ſo that the ſame be done before the Rules be out for pleading in ſuch Action.</p>
            <p n="18">18. And for the reliefe of diſtreſſed Widdows that have no Joyntures,
<note place="margin">By the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law the Widdow can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not intermedle with the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of her husband till her dower aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the proceſſe is ſo delatory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as that ſhe may perhaps be two or three yeeres before ſhe ſhall have her Dower aſſigned by Law, beſides the great charge, and twenty acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents may abate the ſuit to ſet her how to begin and loſe her coſts, as death of Tenants, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, entry upon any part of the Lands, &amp;c.</note> they humbly propoſe, that it may be lawful for them to hold and enjoy all the Lands whereof the huſband died ſeized of any eſtate in Fee-ſimple, or Fee taile in Demeſne in common with the heire, until ſuch time as the heire ſhal aſſigne her or them Dower to the value of a ful third part thereof in ſeveralty, and that of all Rent and other Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſervices whatſoever, whereof ſhe is Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and the huſband dies ſeized, ſhe may take and ſeize, or have and maintaine all Action of Debt, or diſtreine and avow for a third part thereof, until ſuch aſſignment. And that this propoſall may extend to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165789:11"/>Coppyhold Lands where the wife is Dowable, as wel as Freehold.</p>
            <p n="19">19. And for the avoyding many unneceſſary,
<note place="margin">At Common Law <hi>ſolvit ad diem,</hi> or <hi>nil debet</hi> is no plea to a ſimple ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation or Bil, becauſe the ſame is not of ſo high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that if the Plantiffe were knaviſh in all the caſes in this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, he might force the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant into <hi>Chancery,</hi> where both Plaintiffe and Defendant ſpend on the Defendants part.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix, and coſtly ſuits in Equity, they humbly propoſe, that to all Bils, Bonds, and other ſpecialties for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of money, or delivery of goods, or ware which are payd or delivered, and accepted by the Plaintiffe, though not at the time and place, <hi>nil debet per primam</hi> may be a good plea for the Defendant. And that in all other caſes the Defendant may plead or alledge <hi>quae priſt à payer,</hi> and tender in Court the principall debt, or other duty, with Intereſt and charges; or if part onely be paid, or delivered and accepted, the Defendant may be admitted to alledge the ſame, and alledge <hi>priſt à payer,</hi> or deliver for the reſidue, and tender in Court the reſidue of the debt or other duty, with intereſt and coſts; and that in both caſes the Plaintiffe ſhal accept thereof, or be clearly barred of his Action in caſe he ſhal take iſſue thereupon, and it be found againſt him; and that like pleading and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be allowed and received upon Mortgages within ſeven yeeres, or ſome other certaine time or number of yeers after forfeitures; and that after ſuch time elapſed no Mortgage may be redeemable either at Law or in Equity.</p>
            <p n="20">20. And further they humbly propoſe that to take away occupacy, eſtates for life may be deviſeable,
<note place="margin">By the Law at this day, if a man that holds for another mans life hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to die, and have not aſſigned over his Eſtate, he that next happens poſſeſſion, though a ſtranger, in ſtrict Law goes away with the ſtate; wherein though the Law directs the ſtate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very juſt ground, viz. that <hi>in equali jure melior eſt conditio poſſidentis,</hi> yet becauſe many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences happen hereby, this Propoſall is ſubmitted to judgement.</note> and in fault thereof diſcendable to the heire, and make the heire ſubject and lyable to the debt of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, to the value thereof.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165789:12"/>
            <p n="21">21. And laſtly, where as the Parliament hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enacted, that the Defendant may in all eaſes plead the generall Iſſue,
<note place="margin">For if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant being an Executor ſhall plead <hi>non eſt factum</hi> to a Bond, which is conceived to be the generall Irſue, the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe ſhal be put to prove the Bond ſealed and delivered, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, and hath aſſets, and then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant may prove pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or that the Bond was made <hi>per dures</hi> &amp;c. and many other caſes are brought within the ſame miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> and give the ſpeciall matter in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which they humbly conceive may be of great benefit and eaſe to the Defendant, yet it may be of infinite inconvenience to the Plaintiffe, who thereby wil be neceſſitated to very great charge in bringing to the trials of ſuch Iſſues many witneſſes that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might have been ſpared; beſides the many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that wil inevitably fall upon the Plaintiffs, to the loſſe or hazzard of their cauſes. For the preventing of which miſchiefe, it is humbly propoſed, that by way of ſupplement to that Act it may be provided, that in all caſes where the Defendant ſhal plead the general Iſſue, and intends upon the trial to relie upon any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall matter, the Defendant or his Attorney pleading ſuch plea, ſhal upon the tender of the ſaid plea, or at leaſt fourteen daies before the trial of ſuch Iſſue, give a note in writing under one of their hands to the Plaintiffe or his Attorney of the contents of ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial matter, whereupon the Defendant wil relie at the trial of the ſaid cauſe, and to be concluded to give in evidence any other ſpecial matter whatſoever, and that the Defendant may not upon any trial relie upon two ſpecial matters of juſtification; and that that act may not extend to <hi>Replevins,</hi> nor that the Plaintiffes put to prove any thing in relation to the maintenance of his Action, that ſuch ſpeciall matter had admitted, if duely pleaded.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
